家族是自然界中最强大的力量之一
The family is one of the most powerful forces in nature.
家族生活充满非凡奇迹
Family life is full of wonder...
和谐美丽
beauty...
戏剧张力
and drama.
在过去四年里  我们追踪
For the past four years, we've been following
地球上最为著名
some of the most celebrated
最为濒危的几类物种
and endangered species on Earth.
我们追踪它们的命运故事
We followed their fortunes
从津巴布韦的广阔平原
from here on the plains of Zimbabwe,
到印度的茂密丛林
to the jungles of India...
从撒哈拉的沙漠边境
from the edge of the Sahara...
到南极洲的冰冷荒原
to the frozen wastes of Antarctica.
我们记录下每个动物家族的关键时期
We join each family at a crucial moment in their lives
记录下它们与命运抗争
when they are battling against the odds,
为生存拼搏
fighting for survival,
既要与自然力量抗衡
against the elements...
又需同竞争对手战斗
and against rivals.
我们前所未有地从更近距离
We've got closer, and filmed in greater length,
拍摄更长时间
and in more detail,
捕捉到更丰富细节
than we've ever tried to do before.
在现代世界  保障下一代的生存
In our modern world, ensuring the survival of the next generation
变得愈发艰难
is becoming ever more difficult.
对于这些家族  战胜困难创造奇迹
For these families, to win against the odds
将是它们最大的挑战
will be their greatest challenge.
这里是《动物王朝》
This is Dynasties.
西非  塞内加尔
Senegal, West Africa.
一群非同寻常的黑猩猩安家于此
Home to a remarkable troupe of chimpanzees.
这里极为炎热干燥
It gets so hot and dry here.
已是它们生存的极限
It's the very limit of where they can survive.
这片领地由一位强壮坚毅的领袖统治
This territory is ruled by one strong and determined leader,
一只名为大卫的雄性首领
an alpha male known as David.
居于统治地位使它尽享一切
His rule gets him the best of everything,
但它谁也不能信任
but he can trust no-one.
周围强敌环伺  时刻准备取而代之
He's surrounded by rivals prepared to kill him for his crown.
这是一个关于权力
This is a story of power,
政治
politics,
与生存之战的故事
and the fight for survival.
大卫残破的耳朵证明
David's torn ears are testament
它曾为捍卫地位和家族
to the many battles he's fought and won
身经百战并赢得胜利
to protect his status and his family.
它已领导整个族群三年
He has ruled over his troupe for three years.
通常  首领的在位时间不会比这更长
Leaders here don't usually hold power for much longer than this.
眼下  随着旱季来临
And now, as the dry season begins,
大卫的竞争对手又开始集结
David's rivals are gathering again.
成功的雄性首领
Successful alpha males
通常有许多盟友支持它们
normally have many allies to support them.
但大卫只有它自己
But David is alone.
它从未像现在这样处于弱势
He has never been more vulnerable.
在旱季  这些大型土丘牢牢吸引着
In the dry season, these huge mounds of earth are magnets
族群里所有三十二只黑猩猩
for all 32 chimps in the group.
这些土丘满藏
The mounds are full of food,
富含脂肪和蛋白质的食物
rich in fat and protein...
白蚁
termites.
这些黑猩猩已学会使用草秆
These chimps have learned to use grass stems
作为工具掏取昆虫
as tools to fish out the insects.
身为首领  大卫可任意选择进食位置
As leader, David gets his pick of the feeding spots.
但它相当谨慎
But he is wary,
因为它必须在宿敌身边进食
as he must feed alongside old enemies.
它有两位极富野心的对手
He has two particularly ambitious rivals.
大卫的脚趾开始抽动
David's toes begin to twitch,
这种紧张抽搐它无法掩饰
a nervous tic he can't conceal.
这是简普金  它对最高权位觊觎已久
This is Jumkin, who has long-sought the top spot.
还有卢瑟
And this, Luthor...
一只暴躁的年轻雄性
a tempestuous younger male
它生性好斗
with an aggressive streak.
几个月来黑猩猩族群第一次聚集
The troupe is together for the first time in months
争夺好的进食位置很容易引发冲突
and jostling for good feeding spots can easily lead to clashes.
此时由大卫出面维持秩序
It's vital that David keeps order,
并化解矛盾显得尤为重要
and defuses the situation.
所有目光都聚焦于它
All eyes are on him.
它的表现宣告一切由他掌控
His display shows he is in control.
但在黑猩猩社会
But in chimp society,
只依靠力量是不够的
strength alone is not enough.
大卫必须用政治手段来巩固权力
David must be political to hold on to power.
它需要结交盟友
He needs to make an ally.
这是卡尔
This is KL.
它很强壮但胡须灰白
He's strong but grey-bearded
已过了争夺领袖地位的年纪
and past the age where he would challenge for the role of alpha.
大卫开始进行试探
David makes an approach.
梳理毛发能建立友谊的纽带
Grooming builds bonds of friendship...
获取支持  并给予回报
buying support and giving benefits in return.
你给我挠背  我也给你挠[互利互惠]
You scratch my back, and I'll scratch yours.
只有时间才能证明新的结盟是否成功
Only time will tell if this new alliance will pay off.
气温飙升
Temperatures soar.
已达四十度
It's already 40 degrees.
对幼年黑猩猩来说
The arid land might seem
干燥的大地是供玩耍的巨大沙坑
one giant sandpit for the infants,
但对于成年黑猩猩
but for the adults,
潜伏已久的紧张局势开始浮现
existing tensions are starting to surface.
大卫关注着简普金的动静
And David has his eye on Jumkin.
简普金袭击了一位老年雌性同类
Jumkin attacks an elderly female.
这宣告了它对权力的渴望
It's a display of his aspirations for power.
大卫无法容忍
David can't tolerate this...
而卡尔在此时介入
but KL steps in...
给了简普金一个严厉的教训
..And gives Jumkin a sharp lesson.
大卫紧随其后
It's swiftly followed by one from David himself.
随着最后一个猛扑
With a final, huge lunge at his rival...
简普金砰然倒地
...Jumkin comes crashing down.
大卫和卡尔联手起来
Together, David and KL are now
是一股不可小觑的力量
a force to be reckoned with.
大火摧毁了族群四分之三的领地
Fires destroy three quarters of the group's territory.
它们大部分的食物和住所都不复存在
Much of their food and shelter has gone.
随着气温继续升高
And with temperatures continuing to rise,
水愈发稀缺
water is becoming perilously scarce.
族群必须团结一致才能生存下去
The group must stick together to survive.
聚集在干涸的河床上
Gathering in a dried out riverbed,
它们运用代代相传的智慧
they use knowledge passed down from generation to generation.
焦土之下有一处隐藏的水源
A hidden water source under the parched earth.
对大卫来说  干旱不是唯一的问题
For David, there is more than just drought to worry about.
它无法避开它的对手
He can't avoid his rivals.
卡尔成了大卫的忠实盟友
KL is proving to be a loyal ally to David.
此刻大卫无比需要卡尔的支持
And David is going to need him more than ever.
极其罕见地  七只雌性黑猩猩中的三只
By rare coincidence, three of the seven females
同时进入发情期
have become sexually receptive at the same time.
它们肿胀的生殖器吸引着所有雄性黑猩猩
Their swellings attract the attention of all the males.
雌性会尽可能多地与不同的雄性交配
The females will try to mate with as many males as possible.
大卫必须控制它们
David must control them all
确保自己是唯一的交配对象
to ensure he is the one who mates.
但有些成员  比如卢瑟  却另有打算
But some of the troupe, like Luthor, have other ideas.
所有雄性猩猩都将此视为它们的机会
All the other males see this could be their chance.
此刻对大卫来说  捍卫自己的权利
There's never been a more important moment for David
至关重要
to assert his power.
它首先发起攻击
He makes the first move.
而对手们亦通过展示自己的力量来回应
His rivals respond with their own display of strength
他们开始团结一致
and start to close ranks.
大卫和卡尔似乎寡不敌众
David and KL seemed to be outnumbered.
局面陷入一片混乱
Everything turns to chaos.
夜晚某时
At some point during the night,
年轻的雄性猩猩向大卫发起了攻击
the younger males turned on David.
雌性猩猩和它们的幼崽来到它身边
The females and their infants come to his side
支持它  照料它的伤势
to support him and tend his wounds.
它们不能留在这
They can't stay here.
它们和幼崽需要水源
They and their young need water.
整个族群将迁移到距离最近的水坑
The whole group move on to the nearest water hole.
卡尔也不得不离开大卫
Even KL has to leave David behind.
距离下个水源地要跋涉十公里
It's a six mile trek to the next source of water.
大卫被留下等死
David is left for dead.
首领位置出现空缺
There is now a power vacuum at the top
卢瑟视此为良机
and Luthor sees an opportunity.
在族群中制造恐惧是成为首领的途径之一
Creating fear within the group is one way to become leader.
它试图恫吓族群
He tries to intimidate the group,
但争夺首领之位从不是一蹴而就
but a bid for leadership is never instant.
它必须坚持作势数日
He'll have to keep this up for many days.
无依无靠  伤痕累累
Friendless and wounded,
大卫仍然振作起来寻找食物
David somehow musters the energy to search for food.
在被彻底流放前它必须回到族群中去
He has to rejoined the group before he's exiled for good.
但首先  它得恢复体力
But first, he must regain strength.
剩下的时间已不多
Time is running out.
令人惊叹的是  攻击发生后一周
Remarkably, one week after the attack,
大卫踏上搜寻族群的长途跋涉
David makes the long journey to find the group.
与此同时  卢瑟
Luthor, meanwhile,
逐渐提升了自己的领导地位
has ramped up his bid for leadership.
大卫还差一步
David has almost made it...
但此时它已无力再战
..But he's in no fit state to fight.
卢瑟发现了大卫
Luthor spots David's approach...
随时准备应战
..and readies himself for battle.
面对卢瑟  大卫唯一的机会
David's only chance against Luthor
就是尽量使自己看起来强大
is to make himself look as strong as possible.
心生胆怯  卢瑟只得逃跑
Intimidated, Luthor has to run.
没有使出一招一式
Without a blow being struck,
大卫凯旋归来
David is back!
大卫终于和战友卡尔重聚
David is finally reunited with his comrade, KL.
它们为彼此梳理毛发以加强友谊的纽带
Grooming each other reaffirms their bonds of friendship.
对大卫来说  回归只是成功的一半
For David, returning is only half the battle.
负伤疲惫的它
Exhausted and fragile,
在族群中的地位岌岌可危
he's only hanging on to his leadership by a thread.
卢瑟似乎认输了
Luthor appears defeated.
它采取顺从的姿态
With a submissive gesture,
希望得到大卫的原谅
he seeks forgiveness from David.
但大卫不愿接受
But David is unwilling to accept.
接下来的几周  卢瑟发现自己被排挤了
Over the following weeks, Luthor finds himself sidelined.
其它的雄性猩猩如今聚集在大卫身边
The other males now gather around David.
卢瑟别无选择  只能俯首顺从
And Luthor has no choice but to step in line.
大卫重新登上了族群首领的位置
David has his group around him once more,
但它没有对外暴露自己的羸弱
but he doesn't show them how weakened he really is.
它的伤口还未愈合
His injuries haven't healed
其它雄性猩猩随时可能再次发起攻击
and the males could turn on him again at any moment.
但此刻  它还能骗过大家
For now, he seems to be fooling them all.
它争分夺秒地重拾往日力量
He's buying himself time to regain his strength
希望在下一只雌性猩猩发情前恢复体力
before another female comes into season
因为那时它又将面临挑战
when he will face competition once again.
终于  饱含雨水的云层
At last, rain-filled clouds
结束了干旱
bring an end to the drought.
大卫的领地重焕新生
David's territory is transformed.
水源充沛
There is water everywhere
食物充盈
and a glut of food.
族群的生存压力减轻了
The pressure on the group is lifted.
在经历了数月的艰辛之后
Everyone can relax a little
大家都可以放松一些
after months of hardship.
大卫的身体又强壮起来
David's strength appears to be returning.
它在族群面前越来越果断自信
His displays in front of the group become ever more assertive.
但实际上
But in truth,
它比表现出来的样子要虚弱
he remains weaker than he lets on to the others.
一有机会它就会消失去收集额外的食物
Whenever possible, he disappears to gather extra food.
找到什么吃什么
He gorges on everything he can find...
水果
Fruit...
树叶
Leaves...
甚至蚂蚁
Even ants.
它基本恢复健康了
He's almost back to full health.
但只是这样还不足以帮助它
But that alone might still not be enough for him
握紧权利
to hold on to power.
很快又有雌性黑猩猩准备好要交配
Soon, another female will be ready to mate.
上一次  一位盟友对大卫来说显然不够
Last time, one ally was not enough for David.
它要尝试新策略
He tries a new strategy.
它开始给其他雄性黑猩猩梳毛
He starts grooming other males.
一开始一位
First one...
然后另一个
Then another.
慢慢地几周过去后  它的身边逐渐
Slowly, over weeks, he surrounds himself
聚集起一群支持者
with a band of allies.
一支由年长黑猩猩组成的军队
An army of elders...
都是打架老手
Experienced fighters,
但又太老  不足以篡权
but too old to steal his crown.
现在它只能静待  看它采取的措施
Now, he must wait and see if he's done enough
是否能够阻止下一次的阶级挑战
to prevent a recurrence of dissent in the ranks.
果然没多久就有一只雌性进入交配季
Sure enough, a female has come into season.
它肿胀的生殖器让人难以不加注意
Her swelling doesn't go unnoticed.
上一次  大卫处于弱势
Last time, David was vulnerable.
这一次它有了众多同盟
This time, he has allies...
时刻准备着冲锋在前  为它理清道路
Prepared to charge ahead and clear his path.
大卫展示着自己的力量
Displaying his strength
提醒它的对手最好离远一点
reminds rivals to stay away.
如果大卫作为头领足以服众
If David has fully secured his position as Alpha,
那么它将是与那只雌性交配的黑猩猩
he will be the one who mates with the female.
它俩眼神交接
She catches his eye.
在一众同盟者分散就位后
With a number of allies positioned throughout the group,
没有胆敢挑战它的敌人
none of his rivals dare to challenge him.
轮到大卫交配了
This is David's time to mate.
九个月后
Nine months later...
一只雄性幼崽诞生了
A new baby boy!
这是大卫成功捍卫领导权的奖励
David's reward for maintaining power.
它的统治和它的王朝得以延续
His rule and the future of his dynasty is secure.
作为头领  大卫将有比族群里
By being Alpha, David will have sired
其它雄性多一倍的后代诞生
twice as many offspring as any other member of the group.
未来某天  它的某个儿子也许有本事
And one day, one of his sons might just have what it takes
能成为下一位头领
to be a future leader.
大卫是这个黑猩猩族群里最强大
David has become the most powerful, longest reigning alpha,
统治时间最久的头领
this group has ever seen.
但永远会有下一个旱季的到来
But there will always be another dry season,
永远会有对手
and there will always be rivals
在静静等待它们的机会
waiting for their chance.